<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A heavenly proclamation to fly Romish Babylon A sermon preached at Oxford in St Maries Nov. 21. 1613. By Sampson Price Master of Arts of Exeter Colledge and preacher to the citty of Oxford.</title>
            <author>Price, Sampson, 1585 or 6-1630.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1614</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 81 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10077</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20331</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S115216</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99850435</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99850435</idno>
            <idno type="VID">15637</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10077)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 15637)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 585:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A heavenly proclamation to fly Romish Babylon A sermon preached at Oxford in St Maries Nov. 21. 1613. By Sampson Price Master of Arts of Exeter Colledge and preacher to the citty of Oxford.</title>
                  <author>Price, Sampson, 1585 or 6-1630.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 43 [i.e. 34], [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Ioseph Barnes,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1614.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Cf. Folger catalogue, which gives signatures: [par.]²  A-D⁴ E² .</note>
                  <note>P. 34 misnumbered 43.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: A heavenly proclamation to fly from Romish Babylon.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:15637:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15637:1"/>
            <p>A HEAVENLY PROCLAMATION TO FLY ROMISH BABYLON.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi> SERMON PREACHED AT OX<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford in S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> MARIES <hi>Nov. 21.1613.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>BY SAMPSON PRICE <hi>Maſter of Arts of Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Colledge and Preacher to the City of Oxford.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>2. COR. 6. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</bibl> 
               <hi>Wherefore come out from among them, and be yee ſeparate ſaith the Lord, and touch not the vncleane thing, and I will receiue you.</hi>
            </q>
            <figure>
               <p>AC: OX</p>
               <figDesc>printer's device of Joseph Barnes</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>AT OXFORD,</hi> Printed by Ioſeph Barnes. 1614.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:15637:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15637:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVL AND TRVELY WORTHY KNIGHT. SIR ROGER OWEN, <hi>all happyneſſe.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>IR the <hi>miſtery</hi> of <hi>iniquity</hi> doth now worke.<note place="margin">Gr. l. <hi>4.</hi> ep. <hi>38.</hi>
               </note> Never was <hi>Antichriſt</hi> and his army of <hi>Prieſts</hi> (as <hi>Gregory</hi> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth them) more enraged to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugne the true Church the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in theſe <hi>daies,</hi> conceauing in likely hoode that he hath but a <hi>ſhort time,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 12.12.</note> and that the time is <hi>at hand,</hi> which the Lord <hi>hath promiſed,</hi> ſhal bring vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Babel</hi> the vengeance of <hi>the Lord</hi> and the vengeance of <hi>his temple.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier 51.6.11. Rev. 18.20.</note> The Lord make good his <hi>word</hi> &amp; haſten his <hi>worke</hi> that the <hi>heavens</hi> may reioice, and the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> and <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets. Rome</hi> was ſometimes <hi>famous</hi> for her <hi>faith,</hi> but now it is become <hi>Babylon</hi> as <hi>Ierome</hi> in his time confeſſed,<note place="margin">Hier. ad Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell viduam &amp; praef. l. Didimi de Spir. Sancto. Euſeb. l. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>26.</hi> &amp; l. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>21.</hi>
               </note> praiſing God, that he was <hi>freed</hi> from it. It co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceived about the times of <hi>Traian</hi> ſaith <hi>Egeſippus,</hi> and now hath brought forth the man of ſin whoſe <hi>pride,</hi> doing reverence to no mortal man. <hi>Cerem. Rom. l.</hi> 3. <hi>Sect.</hi> 1. <hi>fol.</hi> 120. and his <hi>challendge</hi> of the ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of <hi>ſupreame</hi> and <hi>immediat Pastour,</hi> are badges of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt Gr, l.</hi> 6. <hi>ep.</hi> 30. This <hi>purple Idoll,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reg. Indict. <hi>15.</hi>
               </note> cauſeth <hi>traditions</hi> to be matched with the <hi>written</hi> word of God, and is therein <hi>iniurious</hi> to the <hi>wiſdome of God;</hi> he cauſeth mans merits to bee mingled with the <hi>merits</hi> of Chriſt therein <hi>iniurious</hi> to the <hi>grace of God;</hi> he cauſeth <hi>divine worſhip</hi> to be communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated to <hi>ſtockes and ſtones,</hi> therein <hi>iniurious</hi> to the <hi>glory of God.</hi> Thus the daughter of <hi>Syon</hi> is become the Whore <hi>of Babylon.</hi> In the councell <hi>of Lateran</hi> ſtrict charge was gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to all <hi>Preachers</hi> that none ſhould ſpeake of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of <hi>Antichriſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Caranza ſeſſ. <hi>11.19.</hi> Dec. <hi>1516.</hi> Praeſide Leone. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> which <hi>prohibition</hi> argued the guilt of their <hi>conſciences.</hi> But now the <hi>Pope hath</hi> his <hi>followers</hi> in tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph to giue him <hi>the number of the beaſt</hi> as thoſe books of <hi>Benedictus de Benedictis Bononiae excuſ. Anno.</hi> 1608. and
<pb facs="tcp:15637:3"/>
               <hi>Theſes Caraffae Neapoli excuſae</hi> 1609.<note place="margin">Take the nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meral letters V. 5. L. 50. V. 5. V. 5. l. 1. C. 100. D 500 &amp; it is the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the beaſt 665. Rev. 13.18.</note> dedicated vnto him with this <hi>inſcription PA<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LO V. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ICEDEO,</hi> do ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently proue, as is vrged by that <hi>Noble Phillip Mornai;</hi> Some would haue <hi>Antichriſt</hi> to be but one man ſtanding vpon the greeke article <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. 1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 2.18. It is in <hi>Bell. l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 2. <hi>de Rom. Pont.</hi> By as good reaſon there ſhould bee but one <hi>Davell</hi> becauſe Chriſt ſaith <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, The <hi>Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary</hi> came <hi>&amp; ſowed tares, Mat.</hi> 13.25. &amp; but one righteous man, becauſe <hi>S. Paul</hi> ſaith, that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, The <hi>man of God may be abſolute.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Tim. 3.17.</note> How truely <hi>many Popes of Rome</hi> haue deſerved <hi>this name</hi> I haue laboured to prooue in this <hi>Sermon</hi> which I preſent vnto your <hi>Worſhip.</hi> I confeſſe the <hi>argument is</hi> great &amp; know that the <hi>blame</hi> of <hi>imperfection</hi> is ſo much the more when it lighteth vpon a <hi>high choiſe.</hi>
               <note place="margin">D. Sutcliffe D Abbot. D. Downam. M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> G. Powel.</note> But this <hi>ſubiect</hi> being handled ſo <hi>plentifully</hi> by many <hi>worthies</hi> in our Church, I <hi>vndertooke</hi> the burthen the more <hi>willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> and now offer <hi>this mite (Talents I haue none)</hi> into the publique <hi>treaſury.</hi> I was importuned to publiſh this Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon by ſome <hi>learned</hi> and <hi>religious friends, leaſure</hi> fitted not ſince the preaching of it ſo <hi>opportunely</hi> as now. I dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate it to you as the <hi>chiefe Patron</hi> of my ſtudies by whoſe <hi>means</hi> I obtained my ſetled abode in <hi>this place.</hi> That Hon. <hi>Iudge your Reverend Father</hi> did countenance &amp; <hi>encourage, my</hi> aged and <hi>painfull Father</hi> in his <hi>Miniſtry</hi> in that flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing towne of <hi>Shrewsbury.</hi> Since, your <hi>favours</hi> haue beene <hi>extraordinary</hi> and <hi>bountifull.</hi> Accept from me, I beſeech you theſe <hi>ſmall fruits</hi> of my ſtudies, as a pledge of my true <hi>obſervaunce, vnto you, being a ſincere lover of the truth, &amp; generally honoured for your excellent learning.</hi> So wiſhing to your <hi>good worſhip</hi> the encreaſe of all <hi>good gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> and bleſſings, as alſo to your <hi>elect Lady</hi> &amp; <hi>ſweet oliue-branch,</hi> I take my leaue.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>From my ſtudy at Exeter Colledge, <date>Oct. 28.1614.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your Worſhips in all humble duty at commande <hi>SAMPSON PRICE.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:15637:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>REVEL. 18.4.</bibl>
               <q>
                  <hi>And I heard another voice from heaven, ſaying, come out of her, my people, that yee be not partakers of her ſins, and that yee receiue not of her plagues.</hi>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He <hi>Almighty</hi> God whoſe throne is <hi>heaven,</hi> the firmament his <hi>pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vilion,</hi> and the earth his <hi>theater,</hi> the <hi>Alpha</hi> and <hi>Omega,</hi> the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and the end, the <hi>firſt</hi> the <hi>laſt</hi> and the <hi>revealer</hi> of ſecrets, Da. 2.22.<note place="margin">Victorin. in A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocal.</note> 
               <hi>Cuius antiquit as im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortalitas,</hi> whoſe antiquity is immortality, gaue an eſpeciall priviledge to his meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger <hi>Iohn</hi> an Apoſtolical <hi>Prophet</hi> to write this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy to all ſucceeding ages, a booke never reiected by any but the groſſeſt Heretiques.<note place="margin">Epiph.</note>
            </p>
            <p>That as he preferred <hi>Abel</hi> before <hi>Cain, Iacob</hi> before <hi>Eſau, David</hi> before <hi>Eliab, Mathias</hi> before <hi>Iudas,</hi> ſo he preferreth <hi>S. Iohn</hi> before al the other Diſciples, in this general charge to his <hi>Church.</hi> And he that made <hi>Moy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> who was a <hi>courtier, Iob</hi> the <hi>Potentate, Samuell</hi> the <hi>Iudge, Eliſha</hi> the <hi>Plowman Amos</hi> the <hi>Neat-heard,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gr. ſuper Ezeck.</note> 
               <hi>Iere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my</hi> a <hi>Prieſt, Iſaiah</hi> of the bloud royal a <hi>Prophet, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew</hi> a Publican, <hi>Peter</hi> a <hi>Fiſher</hi> and <hi>Paule</hi> a <hi>Tentmaker,</hi> all to be <hi>penners</hi> or <hi>preachers</hi> of his word, now inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:15637:4"/>a poore <hi>exile</hi> to write the hiſtory of the <hi>Church</hi> in theſe intricate <hi>viſions</hi> and <hi>revelations</hi> which he ſaw vpon the Lords day.<note place="margin">Pro merito vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luminis laus omnis inferior eſt Rupert. in lib.</note> Where having ſent to the ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven <hi>Churches,</hi> and ſhewed the authors of his <hi>meſſage.</hi> God the <hi>Father</hi> and the <hi>Sonne,</hi> in the 5 firſt chapters, he commeth to <hi>predictions</hi> of things to come, c. 6. <hi>ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignations</hi> of thoſe to be ſaved, c. 7. <hi>Indignations</hi> vpon things to be deſtroied, c. 8.9. His <hi>warrant</hi> to write to many <hi>peoples</hi> and <hi>nations</hi> and <hi>tongues</hi> and <hi>kings,</hi> c. 10. The <hi>Churches Prophets</hi> fighting &amp; falling by the beaſt, yet riſing againe c. 11. <hi>Her</hi> body compared to a <hi>woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> cloathed with the <hi>ſunne,</hi> with the <hi>moone</hi> vnder her feet and a crowne of 12 ſtars vpon her <hi>head,</hi> c. 12. Her <hi>combats,</hi> and they bleſſed that die in the Lord, c. 13.14 Her <hi>threatnings</hi> with 7 golden vials ful of the wrath of God, c. 15. Her iudgements vpon her enimies in general, c. 16. and in theſe 17 and 18 chapt. her <hi>victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> gotten againſt the Romiſh church; wherein <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> converted to the <hi>goſpell</hi> (figured by a mighty <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell</hi> lightning the earth, c. 1.) do <hi>iudicially</hi> decree that <hi>Babylon</hi> muſt fal, for troubling of <hi>ſtates,</hi> for corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in <hi>doctrine,</hi> with which ſhe <hi>poiſoned</hi> other <hi>nations,</hi> &amp; for the immoderate <hi>riches</hi> of her Merchants who ſold both <hi>iuſtice</hi> and the <hi>ſoules</hi> of men,<note place="margin">Rome ſelleth ſoules of men. <hi>Rev. 18.13.</hi>
               </note> ver. 13. The <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters</hi> of God muſt accompliſh it by preaching the <hi>goſpell,</hi> at the ſound whereof <hi>Babylon</hi> falleth as once the wals of <hi>Iericho</hi> at the noiſe of <hi>trumpets</hi> ſounded by the <hi>Prieſts,</hi> and by the <hi>Miniſtry</hi> whereof as it were by the ſpirit of the Lords mouth <hi>Antichriſt</hi> falleth into a conſumptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as <hi>Dagon</hi> once fell before the arke.
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:15637:4"/>calling by this long oratorious exhortation to relin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſh <hi>Babylon</hi> (as <hi>Lot</hi> was warned to leaue <hi>Sodom</hi>) in a continuat ſet ſpeech to 21 ver. a part of which I haue choſen for the ſubiect of my diſcourſe.<note place="margin">Clem. Alex. in locum.</note> 
               <hi>And I heard, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It hath beene the <hi>admirable</hi> wiſdome of the <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty,</hi> never from the beginning to leaue his <hi>Church</hi> without ſome comfortable <hi>promiſe.</hi> So immediatly after the fall of our firſt <hi>Parents,</hi> hee foretold of that <hi>reſtauratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> which ſhould be made by <hi>Meſsias</hi> his ſon,<note place="margin">Gen. 3.</note> as it came to paſſe in the <hi>fulneſse of time.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dan. 7.9.11. Ez 31.</note> So hee fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>told by <hi>Daniel</hi> &amp; <hi>Ezechiel,</hi> of the great trouble which his Church ſhould <hi>endure</hi> by the perſecutions of the divided <hi>Greeke Empire, Alexanders</hi> poſteritie,<note place="margin">Diod. l. <hi>18.</hi> &amp; Appian.</note> eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally the <hi>Kings</hi> of <hi>Egypt,</hi> and <hi>Syria,</hi> which deſcended of <hi>Ptolomeus</hi> and <hi>Seleucus,</hi> whom the Scripture calleth the Kings of the <hi>North,</hi> and the <hi>South,</hi> by the ſpace of 294. yeares, and of the preciſe determination thereof at the comming of <hi>Christ.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So he told <hi>Iſrael</hi> of their great ſervitude, and into<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable <hi>bondage</hi> in Egypt,<note place="margin">Gen. 15.</note> and of the full end thereof after 400 yeares.</p>
            <p>So here he ſent <hi>Iohn</hi> the <hi>Evangeliſt</hi> into a little I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land of <hi>Pathmos,</hi> lying in the <hi>Aegean</hi> Sea, in the 96,<note place="margin">Straho. l. <hi>3.</hi> Euſ l. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>18.</hi>
               </note> yeare of our Lord, to prophecie of the ruine of a my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall <hi>Babylon</hi> (I meane Rome) as <hi>Ieremy</hi> had foretold of the ruine of literall <hi>Babylon. Rome</hi> in this booke co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to <hi>Sodome</hi> for <hi>filthineſſe,</hi> to <hi>Egypt</hi> for <hi>Idolatrie,</hi> C. 11. v. 8. and in my Text to <hi>Babylon</hi> for both. <hi>And I heard, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:15637:5"/>It is <hi>like</hi> to that Ier. 50.8. <hi>Fly from the midſt of Babel, depart out of the land of the Chaldeans:</hi> or that Ier. 51.6. <hi>Fly out of the midst of Babel, and deliuer every man his ſoule: Be not deſtroyed in her iniquitie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And I hear danother voice out of heaven.</hi> It is a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine <hi>inſpiration</hi> to the <hi>Church,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Parap H. Card.</note> admoniſhing the <hi>elect</hi> as the other condemned the <hi>reprobate.</hi> The ordinarie <hi>Gloſſe</hi> interpreteth it of the preaching of the <hi>word. Brocard</hi> of thoſe Scriptures in <hi>Eſay, Ieremy,</hi> and <hi>Sopho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie</hi> tending to this purpoſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Saying come out of her my people. Meyerus,</hi> paralle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth it with that Za. 2.6. <hi>Ho,<note place="margin">Marl. Lyra.</note> Ho, come forth, and fly from the land of the North, ſaith the Lord. Marlorat,</hi> with 1. Co. 7.31. <hi>They that vſe the world, as they that vſed it not. Generally</hi> it is to be vnderſtood of the <hi>companie</hi> of the <hi>wicked;</hi> we muſt leaue them, they are lulled in the <hi>cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle</hi> of <hi>ſecuritie,</hi> the <hi>Divell</hi> cloſeth their eies with igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, filleth their cares with <hi>Sophiſtrie,</hi> covereth their heads with <hi>preſumption</hi> of mercie, and <hi>lardeth</hi> their hearts with the neglect of iudgements; eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally it is applied to <hi>Rome,</hi> which will eaſily appeare to be <hi>Babylon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>That yee bee not partakers of her ſinnes:</hi> either in <hi>conſenting vnto,</hi>
               <note place="margin">H. Card.</note> or <hi>acting of her abominations,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by Gods image is <hi>defaced,</hi> man made a <hi>monster,</hi> and Gods <hi>child</hi> the Divels <hi>Creature.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And that yee receaue not of her plagues. Si non fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eritis participes in culpa,<note place="margin">Hugo Card.</note> non eritis ſimiles in poena.</hi> If ye <hi>partake</hi> not in the offence, yee ſhall not partake in the <hi>puniſhment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:15637:5"/>Thus God, ever will bee revenged vpon <hi>Sinners.</hi> Sinne caſt the <hi>Angels</hi> out of heaven, <hi>Adam</hi> out of Paradiſe. By it <hi>Ruben</hi> loſt his <hi>birth-right, Iudas</hi> his <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postleſhip.</hi> It maketh to men <hi>death</hi> terrible, their <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons</hi> to God execrable, the law to <hi>condemne</hi> vs, <hi>conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> to accuſe vs, &amp; the hand of the higheſt to plague vs.</p>
            <p>The ſumme of which Scripture,<note place="margin">In Ref. Cathol.</note> according to iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicious M. <hi>Perkins</hi> is, <hi>That they who hope for ſalvation muſt avoid the faith and Religion of the Romiſh Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Jn the <hi>words</hi> I obſerue two general parts.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 An <hi>admonition</hi> to forſake <hi>Babylon.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Diviſie.</note> And I heard &amp;c</item>
               <item>2 The <hi>reaſons</hi> for this deſertion. That yee bee not partakers, &amp;c.</item>
            </list>
            <p>In the 1 <hi>Generall,</hi> there is. 1. The inſtrument of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition. A voice from heaven.</p>
            <p n="2">2 The matter of the <hi>admonition.</hi> Come out of her my people.</p>
            <p>In the ſecond generall. 1. The <hi>danger</hi> of <hi>contagion</hi> converſing with the wicked. Leſt yee be partakers.</p>
            <p n="2">2 The danger of <hi>puniſhment</hi> to be inflicted vpon the conſorts and complices of the vngodly. And that yee <hi>receaue not of her plagues.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>In the 1. There is a <hi>heavenly voice ſounded.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>In the 2. The <hi>elect</hi> are called.</item>
               <item>In the 3. An <hi>infection</hi> is threatned.</item>
               <item>In the 4. The <hi>plagues</hi> of the wicked are manifeſted</item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <hi>Of theſe</hi> in their <hi>order,</hi> not what <hi>may</hi> bee ſpoken, but what the <hi>ſhort</hi> time, my <hi>weake</hi> readings, and ſimple, but well <hi>meaning</hi> abilitie, with your <hi>patient</hi> attention
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:15637:6"/>and eſpecially Gods <hi>gratious</hi> aſſiſtance <hi>ſhall</hi> permit. Wherein I ſhall deſire to ſpeake <hi>reſolutely,</hi> yet with <hi>ſubmiſſion</hi> to ſo learned an aſſembly. The cauſe is <hi>Gods,</hi> and my warrant from <hi>heaven</hi> to proclaime this voice as powerfully, as my weakneſſe ſhall ſuffer me.</p>
            <p>It was a vaine challenge of <hi>Galilaeus de Galilaeis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1<hi rend="sup">•</hi> Iae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> to ſummon the ſtarres to come neere him, and to giue him an <hi>account</hi> of themſelues;<note place="margin">Nuntius ſyder.</note> he would heare their <hi>diſcourſes.</hi> And a fond brag of <hi>Keppler</hi> that ever ſince <hi>Tycho Braches</hi> death, hee hath received into his eare that no new thing ſhould be done in <hi>heaven</hi> without his knowledge.<note place="margin">De ſtella in cyg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no.</note> And of him who profeſſed, that he heard that which never man heard beſides, a <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> which <hi>Chriſt</hi> made in praiſe of his father <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> dedicating it to <hi>Adrian</hi> the 6.<note place="margin">Ioſephlna di. Gieron. Gratian.</note> But we are ſure <hi>S. Iohn</hi> heard many ſtrange <hi>voices</hi> from heaven by the trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets of <hi>Angels,</hi> amongſt which this is very remarke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able. It is a voice more ſhrill then that of the <hi>Aegyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian</hi> who from the promontory of <hi>Hiſter</hi> was heard of <hi>Hiſtaeus</hi> Admiral of <hi>Darius</hi> being then at <hi>Miletum</hi> as <hi>Herodotus</hi> fableth,<note place="margin">Melpom p. 163</note> for they that were <hi>dead</hi> a while may heare this <hi>voice</hi> and liue. In the <hi>ſcripture</hi> there is <hi>vox Implorativa,</hi> with my voice I called vpon the Lord.<note place="margin">Pſal.</note> 
               <hi>Vox collaudativa.</hi> A lowd voice ſaying ſalvation to our God which ſitteth vpon the throne.<note place="margin">Rev 7.10.</note> 
               <hi>Vox exhortativa,</hi> cry a lowd, ſpare not, lift vp thy voice as a trumpet?<note place="margin">Iſ. 58.8.</note> 
               <hi>and if any man aske</hi> what the ſhal cry, hee muſt cry as the voice fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>heaven,</hi> ſhall admoniſh him. There is <hi>vox Dei.</hi> To day if yee will heare his voice, harden not your hearts. This was a terrible voice to
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:15637:6"/>
               <hi>Adam</hi> I heard thy voice in the garden and was affraid.<note place="margin">Gen. 3.</note> 
               <hi>Nec vox hominem ſonat,</hi> It is the voice of God, not Man. <hi>Vox Chriſti,</hi> heare him. An oracle from heaven hath proclaimed it twiſe, in the river <hi>Iordan, Mat.</hi> 3. &amp; on the mount <hi>Tabor,</hi> Mat. 17. when we haue heard him, and found him we muſt <hi>take hold</hi> of him chap. 3. In his <hi>word,</hi> we muſt beleeue him, in <hi>baptiſme</hi> indue him, in the <hi>Euchariſt</hi> ſpiritually eate him, in the <hi>poore</hi> relieue him, in his <hi>life</hi> follow him, in his <hi>death</hi> truſt in him, in his <hi>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple glorifie</hi> him, on <hi>earth</hi> affect him, &amp; the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in <hi>heaven</hi> when we haue heard his voice wee ſhall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy him. <hi>Vox Dei &amp; hominis</hi> as here, God ſpeaketh to <hi>Iohn,</hi> and the <hi>Church</hi> to vs from heaven. Whence I collect this doctrine.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The word preached ought reverently to be received in reſpect of the place whence it commeth, which is heauen.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Doct. 1.</note> Not that this is to bee vnderſtoode only of the <hi>place</hi> whither Chriſt aſcended, but alſo of the <hi>congregation</hi> of the <hi>faithfull</hi> where he is in the <hi>midſt.</hi> Io. c. 4. v. 2.4. There is a <hi>throne</hi> in heaven about which are 24 ſeats, and 24 <hi>Elders.</hi> In the 5. ch. v. 10. theſe doe <hi>praiſe Chriſt</hi> that had made them <hi>Kings and Prieſts vnto God,</hi> and they ſhould reigne on the earth, 50. <hi>Ep.</hi> 2.6. The <hi>church</hi> is called heavenly Ieruſalem and in other places the <hi>kingdome of heaven;</hi> ſo that whether God from <hi>heaven</hi> doth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mand <hi>Noah</hi> to make &amp; enter the Arke or that an <hi>Angell</hi> bid <hi>Lot</hi> get him out of Sodom? Whether <hi>Moyſes</hi> importune the <hi>people</hi> to get them from the <hi>tents of Dathan and Abiram,</hi> or the Prophets <hi>Iſaie</hi> &amp; <hi>Ieremy</hi> teach this Scripture for the leauing of <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon,</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:15637:7"/>we muſt heare it as the voice of God comming from heaven.</p>
            <p>As there is a <hi>woe</hi> againſt them that wil not <hi>preach,</hi> and a curſe againſt them that <hi>preach</hi> negligently, ſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them that wil not <hi>heare carefully,</hi> whereby they might avoid <hi>iudgements</hi> and <hi>puniſhments.</hi> There is a threefold voice of <hi>woes,</hi> c. 8.13. <hi>Woe, woe, woe to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of the earth. Woe</hi> vnto the world becauſe of <hi>Poperie,</hi> whereby men are puniſhed in their <hi>ſoules,</hi> they will not goe to the <hi>law,</hi> &amp; to the <hi>testimony,</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they can haue no <hi>light. Woe</hi> vnto the world for <hi>Turciſme,</hi> becauſe thereby thouſandes are <hi>murthered</hi> in their bodies not yeelding to the word, whereby they might avoid the <hi>Lords wrath. Wo</hi> vnto the world becauſe of the <hi>laſt iudgement,</hi> for thereby the natural <hi>worldlings</hi> ſhall be plagued both in body and ſoule in <hi>Hell fire</hi> for evermore, becauſe they harkned not to the ſound of the <hi>Goſpell.</hi> The dangers of all theſe may be prevented by <hi>hearing</hi> this <hi>ſacred</hi> voice, Avoice from <hi>heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label>
               <hi>Acomfort</hi> to all Churches which haue the <hi>voice</hi> of the word amongſt them, whereby they are <hi>forewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned: wherein</hi> if any <hi>people</hi> were truely happy, it is this our <hi>Iland,</hi> which hath the voice of many <hi>criers,</hi> prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the way of the <hi>Lord,</hi> of many <hi>Turtles</hi> mourning betwixt the porch and the altar for the <hi>ſinnes,</hi> ſaying <hi>Spare vs good Lord, ſpare thy people.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioel. 2.17.</note> Wee of this <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 21.6.</note> haue many a faithfull, <hi>Ahimelech</hi> amongſt vs, who rather then <hi>David</hi> ſhould periſh with hunger, will giue vnto him the ſhew-bread of the <hi>Sanctuarie,</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:15637:7"/>though they liue hungerly themſelues. Many a wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy <hi>Miniſter,</hi> who rather then <hi>David</hi> ſhould die with thirſt, will with the hazard of their liues giue vnto him of the water of <hi>Bethlehem.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Sam. 23.16.</note> I deny not, but by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding a man may receaue much <hi>comfort,</hi> and be excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently <hi>prepared,</hi> to get ſauing knowledge: yet the voice of <hi>preaching</hi> is the excellenteſt ordinary means which God hath ſanctified to the <hi>ſalvation</hi> of his chil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dren, and to make them wiſe vnto <hi>ſalvation.</hi> By this the minde of the <hi>ignorant</hi> is enlightned, the memory of the <hi>forgetfull</hi> is <hi>strengthned,</hi> the <hi>heart</hi> of the <hi>obsti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate</hi> is mollified, the <hi>affections</hi> of the <hi>vntoward</hi> are <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced,</hi> the <hi>will</hi> of the <hi>perverſe</hi> is <hi>restrained,</hi> and the <hi>life</hi> of the <hi>vngodly</hi> ſo <hi>changed,</hi> that at the <hi>voice</hi> of a ſimple and ſinfull man, he crieth out with the Iewes, <hi>Men &amp; Brethren, what ſhall we doe.</hi> With <hi>David; I am the man,</hi> with <hi>Saul, I haue ſinned,</hi> and with every private con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert to ſay, <hi>God is in theſe men indeed,</hi> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they preach the heavenly voice. Were it not for preaching the word, where were the vnderſtanding <hi>of it,</hi> conſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>by it,</hi> direction <hi>from it?</hi> Without it how ſhould hard places be made <hi>plaine,</hi> plaine be <hi>applyed,</hi> repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances in it be <hi>reconciled,</hi> or <hi>oppugners</hi> of it bee <hi>confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</hi> Take away <hi>preaching,</hi> and then downe with our ſchooles of learning, our houſes of <hi>prayer,</hi> our obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to <hi>Superiours,</hi> our loue to <hi>equals,</hi> and our right to <hi>heaven.</hi> It is the <hi>power</hi> of God to <hi>ſalvation,</hi> the <hi>pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar</hi> of God in our iourney to <hi>Canaan,</hi> the Angell of God to bring vs out of <hi>Sodome,</hi> the meſſenger of God to prepare his way, the <hi>trumpet</hi> of God to cry downe
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:15637:8"/>
               <hi>Iericho,</hi> and the <hi>caller</hi> to bring vs vnto the <hi>Church</hi> of Chriſt, being illuminated by the ſpirit.</p>
            <p>For it is not the outward miniſtery of the word on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that is able to <hi>convert.</hi> Let the <hi>Preacher</hi> be one of a <hi>thouſand.</hi> Iob. 33.23. for the <hi>excellencie</hi> of his gifts as prompt in the law of God as <hi>Ezra</hi> was, as mightie in the Scriptures as <hi>Apollo's,</hi> as eloquent to quicken &amp; enliue his ſpeech, as if he ſpake with the tongue of an <hi>Angel,</hi> as painefull as <hi>Paule,</hi> who laboured more then all the reſt, as blameles in <hi>converſation</hi> as <hi>Zachary.</hi> Let the people heare never ſo gladly as <hi>Herod</hi> heard <hi>Iohn.</hi> Never ſo earneſtly as the <hi>Iewes</hi> heard the <hi>Prophet</hi> as one <hi>that had a pleaſant voice and could ſing well.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſek. 33.32.</note> Let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> heare never ſo long, as thoſe that heard <hi>Paule</hi> vntill midnight. Let the matter bee handled never ſo excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently, as all the Synagogue wondred at the gratious words which proceeded out of Chriſts mouth. Yet if the Lord giue not a <hi>bleſſing,</hi> it is but the ſavour of death vnto <hi>death. Paule</hi> may plant and <hi>Apollo</hi> water, but God gaue the increaſe. <hi>Therefore</hi> every one muſt pray vnto the Lord for an vnderſtanding heart, that as he would open the mouth of the <hi>Preacher,</hi> ſo alſo by his power, he would from heauen open <hi>the eares and hearts of the whole congregation,</hi> that they may heare this heavenly voice.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label>
               <hi>A Reproofe</hi> of thoſe who hearing the heavenly voice of the <hi>Church</hi> by the mouthes of the Miniſters, whereby their <hi>ſinnes</hi> are plainely reproved, and their conſciences powerfully <hi>convicted,</hi> for a while are as <hi>Agrippa</hi> almoſt perſwaded to leaue their ſwearing, ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:15637:8"/>drunkenneſſe, &amp;c: wil with teares confeſſe their <hi>ſinnes</hi> and promiſe great <hi>reformation,</hi> but preſently al their <hi>good motions vaniſh</hi> like a <hi>morning dew,</hi> they returne to their former <hi>courſes,</hi> as the dog to <hi>his vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit,</hi> They liue but their ſicke <hi>repentance</hi> is <hi>dead, Ipſius poenitentiae agunt poenitentiam, they repent of their repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Amb. de poenit. l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> The preacher is vnto them a voice, &amp; nothing elſe, No voice from <hi>heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But it is <hi>farre otherwiſe</hi> with the godly. If the <hi>Lord</hi> ſpeake they tremble, if his word condemne a ſinne in them they fal downe &amp; mourne <hi>before him</hi> till he for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue it. So were the <hi>Publicans</hi> moved at the prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of <hi>Iohn Baptist,</hi> ſo the <hi>Iewes</hi> were pricked in their <hi>hearts</hi> at the preaching of <hi>Peter,</hi> ſo the <hi>Iaylour</hi> cryed to <hi>Paule</hi> and <hi>Sylas</hi> what muſt I doe to bee ſaved. And good <hi>Ioſias,</hi> his heart melted at the hearing of the <hi>law,</hi> ſo effectual is the word in the hearts of the <hi>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect let</hi> the preacher be never ſo weake and ſinneful, as <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> well obſerveth.<note place="margin">Chryſ. in Mat. hom <hi>6.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>When <hi>S. Auſtens</hi> hearers with great applaus com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended his preaching but mourned not for their ſinnes, he told them. <hi>Folia haec ſunt Nos fructus quaeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus.</hi> Theſe are Leaues, we would haue fruit. So <hi>S. Chryſoſtome,</hi> If yee heare <hi>me with ſorrow</hi> I ſhal be <hi>tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>k<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full</hi> and <hi>glad,</hi> for who can make <hi>me ioyful</hi> but you who made me <hi>ſorrowfull.</hi> He thought as <hi>Ierome,</hi> that the beſt commendations of the <hi>ſpeakers</hi> were the <hi>teares</hi> of the <hi>hearers</hi> at the heavenly voices.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>3</label> Is it ſo that the <hi>voice</hi> of the Church is a <hi>heavenlie</hi> voice, then let not any man be puffed vp with the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:15637:9"/>of his <hi>gifts.</hi> What hath he that is not from aboue? Let not any contemne his <hi>brother</hi> though far <hi>meaner.</hi> God often vſeth weake <hi>meanes</hi> to confounde the <hi>mighty.</hi> Let not any <hi>haue</hi> the perſons of <hi>men</hi> in a factious <hi>admiration</hi> ſaying I am of <hi>Paul,</hi> I am of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pollo,</hi> I am of <hi>Cephas.</hi> But let vs giue one another the right hands <hi>of fellowſhip.</hi> Let vs haue the <hi>Miniſters</hi> in loue for their worke ſake. Let vs be ſwift to <hi>heare</hi> and pray the Lord of the <hi>harvest</hi> to thruſt forth <hi>labourers</hi> into his harveſt. Let vs take heede how we <hi>heare</hi> and pray vnto the Lord to open our <hi>hearts.</hi> For alas, the <hi>hearts</hi> of many are ſo <hi>locked</hi> and <hi>barred</hi> againſt the the word, as the <hi>gates</hi> of <hi>Iericho</hi> were againſt the <hi>Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elits,</hi> when none could go out or enter in.<note place="margin">Ioſh. 6.1.</note> Therfore is the <hi>Lord</hi> ſo earneſt in <hi>knocking, calling, crying</hi> by his voice from <hi>heaven.</hi> He knoweth of what <hi>mettall</hi> and <hi>matter</hi> we are made. This maketh him continue cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing till we <hi>anſwere, ſpeake</hi> ſtill Lord, thy ſervants <hi>heare. Hearing</hi> is neceſſary, for it is the <hi>ſenſe</hi> of diſcipline through which as through the <hi>beautifull gate,</hi> that <hi>heavenly Nymph,</hi> knowledge entreth into the <hi>temple</hi> of the ſoule. <hi>Faith</hi> commeth by <hi>hearing.</hi> They that wil not <hi>heare</hi> are a generation of <hi>deafe adders</hi> that ſtop their eares againſt the voice of the <hi>charmer,</hi> worſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>guilty Adam, raging Saule,</hi> the <hi>ſtiffenecked Iewesi, mpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Herod, vnhappy Felix,</hi> and <hi>irreſolute Agrippa.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Many bleſſings are appropriated to the <hi>hearer,</hi> and as many curſes adiudged to him that will not <hi>heare,</hi> all included in that of <hi>Salomon.</hi> He that turneth away <hi>his eare from hearing</hi> the law,<note place="margin">Prov. 28.9.</note> his very praier ſhalbe <hi>turned</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:15637:9"/>into ſin. Therfore he that hath eares <hi>to heare,</hi> let him heare. See that yee deſpiſe not him that <hi>ſpeaketh,</hi> For if they eſcaped not which <hi>refuſed him</hi> that ſpake on earth, much more ſhall not we eſcape if we turne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from this voice crying fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>heaven.</hi> But this <hi>voice</hi> cryeth <hi>lowder</hi> in the ſecond circumſtance, the matter of the admonition, <hi>Come out of her my people.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is a thing commonly <hi>obſerued,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1<hi rend="sup">3</hi>.2ae.</note> that amongſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>wicked,</hi> there are ſome <hi>children</hi> of God. <hi>Lot</hi> was in <hi>Sodom,</hi> Gen. 14. <hi>Rahab</hi> in <hi>Iericho,</hi> Ioſh. 2. <hi>Iael</hi> amongſt the <hi>Gentils,</hi> Iud. 4. <hi>Obadiah</hi> that feared God greatly &amp; ſaved an hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dreth of the Lords Prophets was the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour <hi>of Ahabs</hi> houſe, 1. King. 18.4. There were Saints of <hi>Caeſars</hi> houſhold, even of <hi>Nero</hi> that cruell monſter; ſo here are many people of God <hi>in Babylon</hi> called from it before the Lord powre out the <hi>vials of his wrath.</hi> The <hi>Doctrine</hi> here is plaine,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Doct.</hi> 2.</note> that <hi>The Lord vſually admoniſheth the elect before he take reve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge on the reprobate.</hi> The <hi>Iudge</hi> of the earth will not <hi>ſtay the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous</hi> with the <hi>wicked,</hi> Gen. 18.25. How inextricable ſoever the <hi>peril</hi> ſeeme to be, the Lord knoweth howe to deliver the <hi>godly</hi> out of temptatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.9. <hi>Noah</hi> from the <hi>flowd, Lot</hi> from <hi>Sodom,</hi> the godly in the <hi>Actes</hi> of the <hi>Apostles,</hi> many in <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> forewarned by a <hi>voice</hi> from heaven to get them to <hi>Pella,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Euſ. l. <hi>3.</hi> c. 5.</note> a city beyond <hi>Iordan,</hi> and here Gods people admoniſhed to leaue ſinneful <hi>Babylon</hi> before it be deſtroyed are ſufficient proofes. Which the ancients deſcribe thus. <hi>Confuſion</hi> cauſed <hi>diviſions</hi> of <hi>Nations, Regions</hi> and <hi>Religions:</hi> of this confuſion <hi>Babylon</hi> of <hi>Aſſyria</hi> tooke the name.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:15637:10"/>
               <hi>Pliny</hi> would haue it a part of <hi>Syria</hi> which hee ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendeth hence to <hi>Cilicia.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pl. l. <hi>5.</hi> c. <hi>12.</hi> l. <hi>16.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Strabo</hi> addeth as farre as the <hi>Pontike</hi> ſea. <hi>Ptolomy</hi> thus boundeth it, on the <hi>North</hi> it hath <hi>Meſopotamia,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Geogr. l. <hi>5.</hi> c. <hi>20</hi>
               </note> on the <hi>West Arabia deſerta, Suſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na</hi> on the <hi>Eaſt,</hi> on the <hi>South,</hi> part of <hi>Arabia,</hi> &amp; the <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſian</hi> gulph. Here was <hi>built</hi> the firſt citty we reade of after the <hi>flowde.</hi> Many <hi>glorious things</hi> are ſpoken of it, yet no Citty of God,<note place="margin">L. <hi>2.</hi> L. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Herodotus</hi> would haue the wals to containe in compaſſe 480 furlongs. <hi>Diodorus</hi> but ſo many furlongs as there are <hi>daies</hi> in the yeere, ſo that every day there was a furlong built, 1300000. workemen imployed therein. The <hi>height</hi> of the <hi>wals</hi> was 200 cubits, the <hi>thicknes</hi> 50, ſo <hi>ſpatious</hi> that <hi>Ariſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle</hi> ſaid it was rather a country then a cittie.<note place="margin">L. <hi>4.</hi> Pol. c. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>It was one of the wonders of <hi>the worlde</hi> in regarde of the many miracles of <hi>art,</hi> the <hi>workes</hi> of <hi>Semiramis</hi> and <hi>Nabuchodonoſer,</hi> who cryed out, Is not this great <hi>Babel</hi> that I haue built, for which prowd wordes hee was preſently adiudged the loſſe of <hi>reaſon.</hi> There hee eſtabliſhed that golden head of the <hi>image,</hi> the ſeat of the <hi>Babylonian</hi> Monarchie, yea Dan. 3. Hee ſet vp an <hi>image</hi> 60 cubits high, and 6 broad inioyning a <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like</hi> idolatrie therevnto, which the three <hi>Saints, Sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drach, Meſhach,</hi> and <hi>Abednago</hi> refuſed, and in a fierie tryall were found to be both <hi>Martyrs,</hi> &amp; <hi>Confeſſours.</hi> As <hi>Babylon</hi> was,<note place="margin">The affinitie &amp; likeneſſe of Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon &amp; Rome, proued thus.</note> ſo now <hi>Rome</hi> is. I muſt confeſſe not properly <hi>Babylon,</hi> in as much as they were two divers Cities: but <hi>Rome</hi> may be called, and is <hi>Babylon</hi> figura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuely, ſpiritually, and by alluſion. For as the olde <hi>Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterne Babylon</hi> did a long time oppreſſe the Church of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:15637:10"/>the <hi>Iewes,</hi> ſo <hi>Rome</hi> this <hi>westerne Babylon</hi> hath long op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed the Church of the <hi>Chriſtians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As <hi>Babylon</hi> had 7. heads,<note place="margin">Dion. Halicar. Sigon. F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>neſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a Sueton. Octau.</note> ch. 17.9. ſo <hi>Rome</hi> bad 7. ſe verall governments 1, by <hi>Kings</hi> 2. by <hi>Conſuls</hi> 3. by <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>viri,</hi> 4. by <hi>Dictators</hi> 5. by <hi>Triumviri</hi> 6, by <hi>Emperours.</hi> Laſtly by <hi>Popes. Babylon</hi> had 7 <hi>mountaines,</hi> ſo <hi>Rome,</hi> therefore called by ſome <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Plut. probl. Rom</note> the citty with 7. <hi>heads,</hi> that is, 7. hils. <hi>Capitolinus, Palatinus, Aventinus, Exquilinus, Caelius, Viminalis</hi> and <hi>Quirinalis.</hi> Neither is it ſufficient to ſay, that it is ſhrunke into the plaine of <hi>Campus Martius,</hi> for though it may be true of the body of the towne yet the <hi>Lateran Church</hi> and <hi>palace</hi> which by a charter of <hi>Gregory 2.</hi> was made the head of all churches almoſt 250. yeeres ſince, after him <hi>by Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us 4,</hi> and lately by <hi>Pius 5,</hi> in which there haue beene held by ſeverall Popes ſome 33. <hi>Provincial</hi> or <hi>Natio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal,</hi> and 4 <hi>Generall</hi> Councels for the raiſing <hi>vp of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichrists</hi> throne, where thoſe two monſters firſt were bred, of Tranſubſtantiation &amp; the depoſing of Kings, this Church ſtands to this day vpon the hill <hi>Coelius.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Babylonians,</hi> when there came any warre, had their <hi>Priests</hi> to conſult with their <hi>Gods</hi> where they might hide themſelues. <hi>Baruch.</hi> 6.48. ſo doe they in <hi>Rome,</hi> otherwiſe the <hi>Virgin</hi> had never taught <hi>Hiacyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thus</hi> what to doe, as they faine of her image.<note place="margin">Severin. de vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta mirac. &amp; act. canon. <hi>12.</hi> H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cynth. l. <hi>1</hi> c. <hi>13.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Babylon</hi> was tearmed the <hi>pride of the Chaldeans,</hi> ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and delicate. Rome was held the glory of the we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterne world, and pride of the <hi>Romanes. Babylon</hi> had all kingdomes in ſubiection to her. Rev. 17.18. <hi>Rome</hi> had the like, for <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> in S. Iohns time was made
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:15637:11"/>an heape of ſtones. The <hi>Babylonians</hi> grew in their pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſperitie, as fat calues in the graſſe, and bellowed as Buls: who hath not heard the like of <hi>Monkes</hi> and <hi>Fryers,</hi> eating, ſaith <hi>Luther,</hi> till they came to be all bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, liuing to do nothing, but eating of the labours of other men: groaning vnder the burden of <hi>Epicuriſme,</hi> ſurfetting and crying, <hi>Heu quanta patimur pro amore Chriſti! Babylon</hi> was a land of Images, where they do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted on their Idols.<note place="margin">Bell. de imag.</note> Ier. 50.38. <hi>Rome</hi> deifieth images as much. <hi>Babylon</hi> was noted for her oppreſſion, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acting of gold.<note place="margin">Rev. 18.13.</note> Iſ. 14.4. <hi>Rome</hi> is infamous, for her co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetouſneſſe and marchandiſing of ſoules. <hi>Babylon</hi> va<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, I ſhall be a Lady for ever, I ſhall not be a widow, nor knowe the loſſe of children, Iſ. 47.7. <hi>Rome</hi> hath the ſame wordes, v. 7. of this Chapter. All that is ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of <hi>Babylon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">In <hi>17.</hi> Apoc. com <hi>1.</hi> ſect. <hi>3.</hi> In Apoc. <hi>14.</hi> Num. <hi>42.</hi>
               </note> fitteth <hi>Rome,</hi> ſaith <hi>Viegas. Ribera</hi> deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not, that Rome is myſticall <hi>Babylon,</hi> he ſaith truth perſwaded him to beleeue it, not only of heatheniſh <hi>Rome,</hi> but alſo of Chriſtian <hi>Rome. Antonius Puccius Clericus Apoſtoli.</hi> 3. Non. Mai. 1515. Seſſ. 10. told <hi>Leo</hi> in the Councell of <hi>Lateran,</hi> that S. <hi>Peter</hi> called <hi>Rome, Babylon.</hi>
               <note place="margin">B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll. l. <hi>2</hi> de Rom. Po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t. c. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Bellarmine</hi> hath no Scripture argument to proue S. <hi>Peters</hi> being at <hi>Rome,</hi> but taking this for a ground that <hi>Rome</hi> is <hi>Babylon.</hi> I omit many teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of <hi>Tertullian, adverſus Iudaeos,</hi> and of S. <hi>Ierome in prologo Dydimi,</hi> and Ep. 17. and in Iſ. 47. of Auſtin <hi>de Civ. Dei, l. 18. c. 22.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is the vnanimous opinion of almoſt all the <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epiſc. Elienſis in ſortura Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> p <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>87.</hi> O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oſ. l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Babylon</hi> and <hi>Rome</hi> had the like <hi>beginning,</hi> the like <hi>power,</hi> the like <hi>greatneſſe,</hi> the like <hi>times.</hi> Looke to
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:15637:11"/>words before my Text. All nations dranke of the wine of the wrath of <hi>Babylons</hi> fornications. What na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tions haue not beene afflicted with <hi>warres, treaſons, cruelties,</hi> and many <hi>calamities</hi> from <hi>Rome?</hi> The <hi>Kings</hi> of the earth committed fornication with <hi>Babylon.</hi> Haue not many <hi>Monarchs</hi> ſuffered themſelues, and their <hi>Kingdomes,</hi> to be corrupted with Romiſh <hi>ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitions?</hi> The <hi>Marchants</hi> of the earth waxed rich with the abundance of the delicates of Babylon. What wealth hath beene caried about by means of Popiſh <hi>pardons,</hi> ſelling <hi>Salvation,</hi> yet are they but gulleries. Once heatheniſh <hi>Rome,</hi> now <hi>Babylon,</hi> ſaith <hi>Petrarch.</hi> For as heatheniſh <hi>Rome</hi> was founded in bloud by <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulus</hi> the firſt builder killing his brother <hi>Remus:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug Civ. l. <hi>15.</hi> c, <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> ſo was Popiſh Rome ſetled in full poſſeſſion by bloud, ſome 607 yeares after <hi>Chriſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Palmerius, Iux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta Bedam <hi>612.</hi> Magdebur. Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> when Pope <hi>Boniface</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained of the Emperor <hi>Phocas</hi> (that murtherer which ſlewe his Maſter <hi>Mauritius</hi>) that the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> ſhould be called the vniverſall Biſhop, &amp; the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> the head of all Churches; ſo that now the <hi>Pope</hi> like heatheniſh <hi>Anius,</hi> will bee <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Prieſt,</hi> a <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Kings,</hi> as <hi>Paul 4, ad Ducem Florent.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rex Anius Rex idem hominum, Phaebi<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>, ſacerdos Virg. Ae. n. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> and Prince of <hi>Priests. Cupers de Eccl. pag.</hi> 25. <hi>Num,</hi> 62.</p>
            <p>Is <hi>Rome</hi> now become <hi>Babylon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vſe.</hi> 1.</note> and is there ſo little hope of <hi>ſalvation there?</hi> O then bleſſe wee the name of the <hi>Lord,</hi> praiſe we him and <hi>magnifie</hi> him for ever, that this our <hi>Church</hi> is freed from that land of <hi>darkneſse</hi> and houſe of <hi>bondage,</hi> where their <hi>holyneſſe</hi> is <hi>hypocriſie,</hi> their <hi>zeale fury,</hi> their <hi>faith vncertaine,</hi> their <hi>chiefeſt ground</hi> vnwritten <hi>tradition.</hi> But our <hi>faith is</hi> the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:15637:12"/>ſame with the <hi>faith</hi> of the <hi>Patriarches</hi> and <hi>Prophets</hi> &amp; righteous <hi>Fathers</hi> from the beginning of the world. Let vs looke vpon them, and <hi>conſider</hi> with our ſelues? Were they <hi>Idolaters, Abel, Enoch, Abraham, Iſaac, Iacob, David?</hi> Had they any to go vnto for <hi>Indulgences</hi> and <hi>Pardons?</hi> Did they one call vpon the <hi>other?</hi> Happy are wee that are in ſuch a caſe to follow theſe <hi>worthies. Bleſſed</hi> are we that haue <hi>God</hi> only to bee our <hi>Father</hi> &amp; this Church to be our Mother. <hi>Rome</hi> was ſometimes a glorious citty, <hi>Ignatius</hi> cald it <hi>Caſtiſſimam, Tertullia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> ſaide it was a <hi>happy</hi> Church becauſe the Apoſtles of <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſuffered <hi>martyrdome</hi> in it,<note place="margin">B Iew. in def. of apol.</note> and left their whole doctrine vnto it, but now ſaith he,</p>
            <q>
               <l>O Roma a Roma quantum mutata vetuſta es</l>
               <l>Nunc caput es ſcelerum quae caput or bis er as?</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Seeing</hi> there are ſome <hi>Godly</hi> amongſt the <hi>wicked,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Vſe.</hi>
               </note> let them ſtriue againſt the <hi>common ſins,</hi> the beſt elſe may be <hi>overtake<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> Hence is it, that for the <hi>warning</hi> of all, for a caveat to <hi>the people</hi> of God, that they <hi>who thinke they ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d</hi> may take heed leaſt they fal, <hi>Criminatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s</hi> as wel as the <hi>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendations</hi> of the beſt are regiſtred in <hi>ſcripture, Noahs drunkennes</hi> as wel as his <hi>vprightnes. Lots incest</hi> as wel as the <hi>grieving</hi> of his <hi>righteous</hi> ſoule. The weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of <hi>Moyſes</hi> at the waters of <hi>Meribah</hi> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſpake <hi>vnadviſedly</hi> with his lippes as well as his <hi>zeale</hi> when he brake the <hi>tables,</hi> comming down from the mount <hi>Sinai. Ionah</hi> his flying from <hi>Tharſis</hi> as wel as his prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching in <hi>Niniveh,</hi> and here the <hi>elects</hi> being in <hi>Babylon</hi> is noted to the world and they publiquely admoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to leaue this cage of <hi>vncleane birds,</hi> this den of <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vels</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:15637:12"/>O the patience of a <hi>mercifull</hi> God never <hi>ſtriking</hi> but firſt <hi>warning,</hi> not ſuddenly <hi>taking revenge!</hi> How patient is he towards many beaſtly Belly <hi>Gods,</hi> and ſwiniſh <hi>drunkards,</hi> that ſeeke to <hi>beſpatter</hi> the blood of Chriſt with their <hi>ſurfets</hi> and <hi>filthie vomits.</hi> Towardes horrible <hi>blaſphemers,</hi> renting him aſunder with their fearefull <hi>oathes.</hi> Towards abominable <hi>Atheists,</hi> who with their damned crew, ſhake their heads at <hi>him,</hi> &amp; like the young ones of <hi>Bethlehem</hi> make a mocke of him. He is provoked every <hi>day,</hi> and yet hee reneweth his <hi>mercy</hi> every day, to al, even to the obſtinat'ſt <hi>Recu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſants,</hi> ſaying, <hi>why will ye die,</hi> which voice many haue apprehended and fled out of Babylon.<note place="margin">Amb. Hexem. l. <hi>6 3.</hi> Ep. l. <hi>7.48.</hi>
               </note> For as S. <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe</hi> reporteth of the <hi>Partridges,</hi> that one ſtealeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the egges of <hi>another</hi> and <hi>hatcheth</hi> them, but, ſaith he, divers of the young being hatched, when they af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward heare the voice of their <hi>own</hi> &amp; naturall <hi>dams</hi> in the field, leaue their <hi>ſtepmother,</hi> and come againe to <hi>her,</hi> to whom by <hi>originall right</hi> they belonged. So ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny, who haue beene infected by the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> after true grace imparted from aboue, returne from their <hi>Seminaries,</hi> and adioyne themſelues to our <hi>hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py</hi> and true <hi>Church,</hi> where wee haue the worde truely <hi>preached,</hi> the ſacraments rightly <hi>administred,</hi> the poor charitably <hi>releeued,</hi> and Gods graces ſo abundantly <hi>beſtowed,</hi> that God hath not dealt ſo with any other <hi>nation,</hi> becauſe we are his <hi>people,</hi> and the ſheepe of his <hi>paſture,</hi> whom he hath called out of <hi>Babylon,</hi> that we might not be partakers of <hi>her ſinnes.</hi> As it followeth in the firſt of my ſecond generall.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:15637:13"/>Amongſt all the <hi>occaſions</hi> of ſinne, there is none more <hi>dangerous</hi> then evill company. For can a man take <hi>coales</hi> of fire in his <hi>boſome,</hi> and not bee burnt, or handle <hi>pitch,</hi> and not be <hi>defiled,</hi> or fly with <hi>Oſtritches</hi> and <hi>Pellicans,</hi> and nor grow wild, or dwel in the tents of <hi>wickedneſse,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chryſoſtome.</note> and not learne to be <hi>wicked? Rerum na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tura ſic est vt quoties bonus malo coniungitur, non ex bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no malus oritur, ſed ex malo bonus contaminatur,</hi> Soo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner the good may be infected by the <hi>bad,</hi> then the <hi>bad</hi> reformed by the <hi>good:</hi> ſo was it like to be in <hi>Babylon,</hi> and therefore the people of <hi>God</hi> are called out, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce this Doctrine ariſeth.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Doct.</hi> 3.</note> 
               <hi>It is the part of Gods children, to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void the company of the wicked, least they be infected by them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This made <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Ioſhua,</hi> ſo earneſtly to exhort the <hi>Iewes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod 34. Deut. 7. Ioh 23. Pſal. 106.35.</note> to make no compact with the other <hi>na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> leaſt they ſhould bee vnto them a <hi>ſnare,</hi> to cauſe them to ſerue other <hi>Gods, and ſo the wrath of the Lord ſhould be kindled against them, and deſtroy them.</hi> Which they not obeying, were mingled amongſt the <hi>Heathe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> and learned their workes. How much more neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry is this doctrine now in the time of Antichriſt, the Lord ſending ſtrong deluſions, that if it were poſſible, the elect might be deceaued.<note place="margin">2. Theſſ. 2.11.</note>
            </p>
            <p>This hath made S. <hi>Paul</hi> and others ſo to preſſe this point. Haue no <hi>fellowſhip</hi> with the vnfruitfull <hi>works of darkneſſe.</hi> Ep. 5.11. Come out from among them and touch no <hi>vncleane thing.</hi> 2. Co. 6.19. Hate the gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that is <hi>ſpotted with the fleſh.</hi> Iude 23. Take heed of the <hi>leaven</hi> of the <hi>Phariſees</hi> and <hi>Sadduces.</hi> Mat. 16.12
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:15637:13"/>For a little leaven leaveneth the <hi>whole lumpe.</hi> 1. Co. 5.6. S. <hi>Baſil</hi> therefore compared the <hi>wicked</hi> to them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected with the <hi>plague:</hi> and Bar. calls it a <hi>ſacriledge</hi> like that of the <hi>Iewes</hi> laying violent hands vpon Chriſt.<note place="margin">Hom <hi>9.</hi> Se. <hi>1.</hi> conv. Pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li.</note> It hurt the <hi>ſonnes</hi> of <hi>Seth,</hi> good men before, but marry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with the <hi>daughters</hi> of <hi>Cain,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 4.6.7.</note> they filled the earth with ſo much <hi>ſinne,</hi> that a <hi>floud</hi> was ſent to cleanſe it.</p>
            <p>A good Prophet ſent to <hi>Bethel,</hi> there breaking the <hi>altar</hi> and reſtoring to <hi>Ieroboam</hi> his withered hand, yet in his returne accompanying with the falſe <hi>Prophet</hi> was kild by a <hi>Lyon.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 King. 13. <hi>Euſ. l.</hi> 3 <hi>c.</hi> 33.</note> The young man commended to a Biſhoppe by S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Iohn,</hi> leaving the Biſhoppe, became a theefe.</p>
            <p>It is the <hi>hardeſt</hi> and moſt <hi>intangling</hi> knot that can bee <hi>knit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug l. <hi>3.</hi> conf. c. <hi>8</hi> Gr. in paſtoral.</note> ſuch are the Divels <hi>Marchants</hi> who in the <hi>markets</hi> and affaires of the world gaine <hi>many ſoules</hi> to hell. Wee may ſee the fruit in <hi>Peter</hi> who denied his <hi>Maſter</hi> amongſt the wicked,<note place="margin">Remig. in Mat. <hi>26.</hi>
               </note> whom he ever confeſſed amongſt the <hi>Apoſtles.</hi> Therefore <hi>Salomon</hi> ſpake wel, the friend of <hi>fooles</hi> wilbe made <hi>like vnto them;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pr. 13. Eccl. 7.</note> and the <hi>wiſe man,</hi> Depart from the <hi>wicked,</hi> and evils <hi>will depart</hi> from thee. So did <hi>S. Iohn,</hi> he woulde not waſh in the <hi>bath</hi> with <hi>Cerinthus;</hi> and <hi>Policarpus</hi> he would not ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute <hi>Marcion</hi> the heretique. <hi>S. Paule</hi> gaue the reaſon,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Euſ. l.</hi> 3.52.</note> 
               <hi>What fellowſhip hath light with darkneſſe or Chriſt with Belial,</hi> 2. Co. 6.15. &amp; the <hi>Prophet</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſed, I hate them that hate thee, with a <hi>perfect</hi> hate <hi>odiendo vitia, dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do naturam,</hi> hating them as they are <hi>ſinnefull,</hi> loving them as they are <hi>men;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gr. <hi>2.</hi> baſt. c. <hi>46</hi> In Ez. ho <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> for it is folly ſaith <hi>Gregory to pleaſe them</hi> who we know diſpleaſe <hi>God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:15637:14"/>
               <hi>Seeing</hi> the company of the wicked is ſo <hi>infectious,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Vſe, 1.</note> and yet there are ſo many,<note place="margin">1. Co. 5.10.</note> that we cannot <hi>avoid them</hi> vnles we go out of the <hi>world,</hi> let vs make a vertue of <hi>neceſſity;</hi> let vs walke without <hi>reproofe in the midſt</hi> of a perverſe <hi>generation.</hi> Of <hi>Noahs</hi> 3 ſonnes one will bee a <hi>mocker</hi> of his father. Of <hi>Abrahams</hi> 2 one a ſcorner of his brother. Of <hi>Iſaacs</hi> 2 one wil be <hi>carnall.</hi> The 11 bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren of <hi>Iacob</hi> will ſell the twelfth <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> but happy is the little flocke <hi>of Chriſt</hi> which ſeparate themſelues as the <hi>beloved people</hi> of God, and leaue the <hi>wicked</hi> having beene hurt by them. The burnt <hi>childe</hi> feareth the <hi>fire.</hi> The fiſh once <hi>wounded</hi> with the <hi>hooke</hi> is alwaies <hi>ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious</hi> of the baits, The <hi>beaſt</hi> that hath once bin <hi>caught</hi> and hath broken the ſnare will hardly bee <hi>intrapped</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine. Hath <hi>nature made</hi> all creatures thus <hi>carefull</hi> to prevent bodyly <hi>dangers</hi> &amp; ſhal not we be more <hi>careful</hi> in the caſe of our <hi>ſouls</hi> that when once by the mercy of <hi>God</hi> we haue eſcaped fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the <hi>filthynes</hi> of the world wee bee not <hi>catched</hi> againe therein leaſt the <hi>latter end</hi> be worſe then the <hi>beginning?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O that all our Engliſh <hi>fugitiues</hi> would looke into this one leſſon, that ſo they might leaue <hi>Rome</hi> which oppoſeth it ſelfe againſt <hi>Chriſt</hi> in <hi>doctrine,</hi> in <hi>diſcipline,</hi> in <hi>life,</hi> ſo that now the <hi>Prophecies</hi> are <hi>fulfilled</hi> &amp; ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny reaſons found true to proue that the <hi>Pope</hi> is <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rog. Houeder. in Rich. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> So <hi>Ioachimus Abbas</hi> told <hi>Rich. 1.</hi> king of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> going to the holy land, that <hi>Antichriſt</hi> was borne in <hi>Rome</hi> and ſhould be advanced <hi>higher</hi> in that See. So <hi>Robert Groſthead</hi> ſometimes Biſhop of <hi>Lincolne</hi> cryed out on his <hi>death bed,</hi> Chriſt came into the worlde to
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:15637:14"/>gaine <hi>ſoules,</hi> if any feare not to deſtroy <hi>Chriſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. Pariſ. in Hen. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> he is An richriſt. He ſpake it, <hi>Anno 1253.</hi> of <hi>Innoc. 4.</hi> who was found dead <hi>in bed</hi> his body ful of <hi>blaines</hi> the day after he heard that voice <hi>Veni miſer in iudicium Dei,</hi> come wretch before Gods iudgement ſeat.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vrban</hi> the 6, and <hi>Clemens</hi> the 7,<note place="margin">Baldus in vit. Pont. l. <hi>3</hi> de pont. c. <hi>15</hi>
               </note> two <hi>Popes</hi> at once called one the other <hi>Antichriſt. That</hi> the <hi>Pope</hi> is <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt, Bellarmine</hi> deſcribeth Antichriſt to be the laſt <hi>king</hi> that ſhall hold the <hi>Romane Empire</hi> yet without the name of <hi>the Romane Emper our.</hi> Did not Pope <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory</hi> 7, ſo, by the confeſſion of <hi>Azorius</hi> the <hi>Ieſuit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Inſtit. moral. part. <hi>2.</hi> l. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>20.</hi> l. ex quo.</note> to the Emperour <hi>Leo</hi> then reſident in <hi>Greece,</hi> excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicating him for breaking down of <hi>Images,</hi> abſolving all his <hi>ſubiects</hi> from their oath of <hi>allegiance,</hi> wherevp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>Romanes</hi> caſting of the <hi>Emperours</hi> yoake did ſolemnely ſweare obedience in all things to the <hi>Pope?</hi> Doth he not commaunde the <hi>Emperour</hi> to holde his <hi>ſtirrup,</hi> ſerue his <hi>table</hi> with the firſt <hi>diſh,</hi>
               <note place="margin">L. Cerem. Eccl. Ro. l. <hi>3.</hi> p. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> and carry him vpon his <hi>ſhoulders?</hi> Did not Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> the 3. ſet his foot vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the necke of the <hi>Emeprour Frederike</hi> the I, miſapplying that in Pſal 91.13.<note place="margin">Sigibert. in chr. Anno <hi>1159.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Thou ſhalt tread vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Lyon. That the Pope is Antichriſt,</hi> as Chriſt choſe <hi>ſimple men,</hi> ſo ſhal <hi>Antichriſt</hi> ſelect <hi>ſubtil</hi> &amp; craf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty men, and experienced in the <hi>knowledge of the world,</hi> ſaith <hi>Gregory.</hi> Doth not the <hi>Pope</hi> ſo?<note place="margin">Moral. in Iob. c. <hi>16.</hi>
               </note> Examine his <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtory of Cardinals, Cloisters</hi> of <hi>Monkes, orders</hi> of his <hi>ſchooles,</hi> and <hi>ſocieties,</hi> all theſe hold it a reproach vnto them if they be not <hi>accounted</hi> moſt ſubtill.<note place="margin">Tolet. Inſtr. ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerd. Parſons in trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe of mitigatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> The <hi>profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours</hi> of mentall <hi>Aequivocation,</hi> I confeſſe excell all <hi>Matchiavellian Polititians</hi> that ever haue bin hard of.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:15637:15"/>
               <hi>That</hi> the Pope is Antichriſt,<note place="margin">Syb. orac. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> ſo <hi>Sybil. oracul.</hi> 8. Hee ſhal be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, he ſhall haue a <hi>white head,</hi> and be called by a name much <hi>like Pontus.</hi> So is the <hi>Pope</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a white miter of <hi>Syluer,</hi> and his name is <hi>Pontifex.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>That</hi> the <hi>Pope</hi> is <hi>Antichrist,</hi> I deſcribe him not as a <hi>Iewe</hi> of the tribe of <hi>Dan,</hi> or one bred vp in <hi>Bethſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da</hi> and <hi>Chorazin,</hi> or as <hi>Mahomet,</hi> or <hi>Nero,</hi> or one building vp the citty <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> or one borne of a <hi>Fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er</hi> &amp; a <hi>Nunne,</hi> or turning trees vpſide <hi>downe</hi> with the tops in the <hi>ground</hi> and <hi>forcing</hi> the roots to growe <hi>vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Blew. in Theſ.</note> flying vp to <hi>heaven</hi> and then falling down brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king his <hi>necke</hi> as ſome haue <hi>opened him;</hi> but working the <hi>myſtery</hi> of <hi>iniquity,</hi> defacing the <hi>ſacraments,</hi> ſelling <hi>pardons,</hi> in all things contrary to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> an Idoll <hi>ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard,</hi> a pandar of all <hi>evils,</hi> to whom even all the <hi>notes</hi> of <hi>Antichriſt</hi> doe agree as is ſufficiently proved by a moſt worthy M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> in this our <hi>Iſrael</hi> in his learned book <hi>Demonſtratio Antichristi.</hi>
               <note place="margin">D. Abbot. M. of Baliol. Col.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>That</hi> the Pope is <hi>Antichrist,</hi> exalting himſelfe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue all <hi>things.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Can. ſi Papa diſt. <hi>40.</hi>
               </note> 2. Th. 2.4. Aboue Biſhops, for none <hi>of them</hi> may ſay vnto him, why doſt thou this, though he lead infinite ſoules to hell; Let <hi>experience</hi> ſpeake. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue <hi>Councels,</hi>
               <note place="margin">I. de benef. p. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> for one may appeale from the councel to the Pope, but not from the <hi>Pope</hi> to the <hi>Councell,</hi> ſaith <hi>Ioh:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bede of prae: og. of. K.</note> 
               <hi>Selva</hi> a Spanyard. Let <hi>experience</hi> ſpeake. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue <hi>Angels,</hi> ſo <hi>Baronius</hi> in his <hi>paraeneticall</hi> againſt the <hi>Venetians,</hi> abuſeth that place to the <hi>cleargy?</hi> Know yee not that we ſhal iudge <hi>the Angels.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Can. Lector. <hi>34.</hi> diſt.</note> Aboue the <hi>Apostles</hi> for he may diſpenſe againſt the <hi>Apoſtles Gl. verbo Fiat.</hi> Aboue the <hi>law,</hi> for the Pope cauſed the 2. comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:15637:15"/>to be razed out in the ſynod of <hi>Ausburg.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Anno</hi> 1548.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Aboue the <hi>Sacraments,</hi> for he may <hi>change</hi> in them what he thinketh meete. Aboue the <hi>Church,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Conc. Trid. Seſſ. <hi>21.</hi> c. <hi>1.</hi> L. <hi>1.</hi> de R. Pont. c. <hi>9.</hi> Can. Nemo iudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cab. can. <hi>9.</hi> q. <hi>3.</hi> Sect. <hi>4.</hi> de Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem. c. <hi>6.</hi> &amp; l. <hi>1.</hi> tit. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> though to the ſhutting out of Chriſt ſaith <hi>Bellarm.</hi> Aboue <hi>Princes,</hi> for no ſecular can <hi>iudge</hi> him. Therefore <hi>bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth He</hi> a ſword vpon the <hi>night</hi> of Chriſts nativity, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving it to ſome Prince his <hi>favorite,</hi> but never ſending them the <hi>law</hi> or <hi>goſpell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I might ſtande to <hi>calculate</hi> the number of the beaſt <hi>expreſſed</hi> in three greeke characters, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>666. c. 13.18. mentioned by <hi>Irenaeus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">L. <hi>5.</hi> c. <hi>25.</hi> L. <hi>2.</hi> de temp. nov. c. <hi>4</hi> p. <hi>157.</hi>
               </note> who had the names of <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>christ</hi> from them that ſaw <hi>Iohn,</hi> ſaith <hi>Acoſta,</hi> he muſt be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. The <hi>Italians</hi> were called <hi>Latini,</hi> which no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth of what countrie the beaſt ſhould come. The <hi>Popes</hi> haue all their <hi>religion, ſervice, prayers, lawes, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees, writings,</hi> and <hi>tranſlations</hi> in <hi>Latine,</hi> they preferre the <hi>Latin</hi> tranſlations of the <hi>Bible</hi> before the <hi>Hebrew,</hi> and <hi>Greek;</hi> originals.</p>
            <p>That the <hi>Pope</hi> is <hi>Antichrist,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev. 13.11.</hi> Faber Stapl. in Inſtit.</note> 
               <hi>Antichrist</hi> muſt haue two hornes like a <hi>Lamb,</hi> and ſpeake like a <hi>Dragon;</hi> ſo is the <hi>Pope,</hi> in words calling <hi>himſelfe ſervant of ſervants,</hi> but indeed ſuffering to be <hi>worſhipped. Antichriſt</hi> muſt haue vpon his <hi>head,</hi> written a name, <hi>Mysterie.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev. 17.5.</hi> Brocard in Ap.</note> The <hi>Pope</hi> hath this word vpon his <hi>Crowne.</hi> Antichriſt muſt ſit in the <hi>Temple of God,</hi> Not that therefore the <hi>Church</hi> where the Pope is <hi>chiefe,</hi> is <hi>Christs</hi> true Church, and therefore all <hi>Protestants</hi> ſhould bee ioyned to it, as <hi>Bellarmine</hi> reaſoneth. But it is called ſo becauſe they whom he hath <hi>ſeduced</hi> were ſometimes the <hi>Temple of God.</hi>
               <note place="margin">L <hi>3</hi> de Pont. c. <hi>13.</hi> Anſel. <hi>2.</hi> Th.</note> As the Temple of <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> was ſo called the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:15637:16"/>place, when the <hi>abomination</hi> of deſolation was in it, not as being ſo <hi>properly,</hi> but becauſe it had beene once <hi>dedicated</hi> to Gods worſhip,<note place="margin">De temp noviſſ. l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>12.</hi>
               </note> ſaith <hi>Acosta.</hi> In the temple of God, that is inſteed of the whole <hi>Church,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Auſtin.</hi> Doth not the Pope ſo profeſſing,<note place="margin">L. <hi>20.</hi> Civ. c. <hi>19,</hi> Gretſ. <hi>2.</hi> coll. Ratisb. Seſſ. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> to define any thing without a <hi>Councell. Antichriſt</hi> deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth that <hi>Ieſus</hi> is come in the <hi>fleſh,</hi> and is Chriſt. 1. Ioh. 2.22. So doth the <hi>Pope,</hi> though not in <hi>grant,</hi> yet in <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inference,</hi> overthrowing the truth of <hi>Chriſts humanity</hi> holding his <hi>whole humane</hi> body locally circumſcribed in <hi>heaven,</hi> &amp; at once (the ſame <hi>inſtant</hi>) wholy preſent in ten <hi>thouſand places</hi> on earth, without <hi>circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcriptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> &amp; that whole <hi>Chriſt</hi> is in the formes of <hi>bread</hi> with all his <hi>dimenſions,</hi> every part hauing his own place &amp; fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure, &amp; yet, ſo that hee is wholy in every part of the <hi>bread.</hi> Denieth our <hi>iustificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> by <hi>faith</hi> in Chriſt, aſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing it to our own works. Denieth Chriſts <hi>ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> as his Proſelites doe, while they hold a payment of our <hi>vtmoſt farthings</hi> in a deviſed <hi>Purgatory.</hi> Chriſts mediation while they <hi>implore</hi> others to aide them. Adoring <hi>Angels, Saints, Bread, Reliques, Croſſes, Images</hi> What offals haue they to allure <hi>Proſelites</hi> out of this <hi>Kingdome,</hi> who with <hi>Noahs</hi> crow fly out of the <hi>Arke,</hi> without any mind of returne, at leaſt without any good mind if they returne, <hi>Immunities</hi> to warrant ſin, <hi>Indulgences</hi> to remit ſinne, <hi>Iubilees</hi> for libertie, <hi>Libels</hi> of contumely, <hi>Exemptions</hi> from <hi>loyaltie, pretence</hi> of conſcience, <hi>promiſe</hi> of <hi>preferment, faculties</hi> for <hi>treaſon</hi> and <hi>murthers</hi> of the Lordes <hi>annointed, facilities</hi> to climb <hi>heaven,</hi> not by <hi>Iacobs</hi> ladder (the <hi>grace</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi>)
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:15637:16"/>but by <hi>merits</hi> of Saints, <hi>ſupererogation</hi> of <hi>workes,</hi> and <hi>pardons</hi> of <hi>Popes,</hi> ſinfull, miſerable, all of them, <hi>abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable</hi> many of them.</p>
            <p>Gr. 9. refuſed the <hi>Goſpell of Chriſt,</hi> and inſteed there of ſubſtituted a legend,<note place="margin">Balaeus l. <hi>5.</hi> vit. Pont.</note> compiled by a <hi>Monke</hi> named <hi>Cyril.</hi> Pope <hi>Paulus Venetus</hi> painted himſelfe,<note place="margin">Plat vil. Adr. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> deſiring to ſeeme a <hi>woman.</hi> Pope <hi>Hildebrand,</hi> Gr. 7. whome all good men ſaw,<note place="margin">Annal. l. <hi>5.</hi> pag. <hi>455.</hi>
               </note> to be of the kingdome of <hi>Antichriſt</hi> (ſaith <hi>Aventinus</hi>) though <hi>Bellarmine</hi> cald him a <hi>Saint,</hi> cauſed Pope <hi>victor</hi> the 2 to bee empoyſoned in the wine of the <hi>Euchariſt,</hi> and caſt his God into the <hi>fire,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Benn Card. vit. Hild Abb. veſp. vit. H <hi>3.</hi> Guicc. Chron. I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal l. <hi>11.</hi> Anno. <hi>1513.</hi> C. <hi>11.</hi> Ann. <hi>954.</hi>
               </note> becauſe it anſwered him not of his <hi>event</hi> in war with Hen. 4. <hi>Leo 10.</hi> vpon the day of his <hi>coronation</hi> ſpent one hundred thouſand Duckets, and called the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell of Chriſt a fable, as <hi>Guicciardine</hi> telleth, <hi>Iohn</hi> the 12 dranke to the <hi>Divell. Luit prand.</hi> rer. Europ. l. 6. c. 6. The whole Councel of <hi>Conſtance</hi> Seſſ. 11. concludeth of <hi>Iohn 23. Atempore iuventutis ſuae,</hi> From the time of his <hi>youth,</hi> he was ever of an <hi>evill diſpoſition, ſhameleſse, vnchaſt,</hi> a <hi>lyar, diſobedient</hi> to his Parents, and given to many other vices. <hi>Innocentius 8,</hi> had 16 baſtards by ſeverall ſtrumpets,</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>Octo nocens pueros genuit totidemque puellas</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Hunc merito poterit dicere Roma patrem.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Marul de In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noe. <hi>8.</hi> Gnic. l. <hi>16.</hi>
                  </note>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p>Many Popes are vſually praiſed <hi>for goodneſse,</hi> not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding others <hi>in wickedneſſe,</hi> ſo they witnes of one, <hi>Bonus Pontifex, nihil memoria dignum reliquit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bened. <hi>1.</hi> Siſini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us. Geneb. l. <hi>4.</hi> Chr.</note> of Ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Niſi podagram habuiſſet neſciremus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Many</hi> haue beene triſed away ſuddenly, it being ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected they would be over <hi>good.</hi> They may haue the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:15637:17"/>
               <hi>teſtimony</hi> of one of their owne who <hi>afterward</hi> was <hi>Pope</hi> himſelfe (<hi>Aene as Sylvius</hi>) If time would permit I could bring forth many <hi>examples</hi> of Romane <hi>Biſhops</hi> that were ſound either to be <hi>Heretiques</hi> or elſe defiled with <hi>other vices,</hi>
               <note place="margin">De geſlis concil Baſil. l <hi>1</hi> de Ro. Pont.</note> yet all muſt be ſtiled <hi>Popes</hi> of godly memory becauſe ſay their <hi>Scribes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gloſſ. Extrav. l. <hi>5.</hi> ca. Du. lum authorized by Gr. <hi>13.</hi>
               </note> we herein reſpect not <hi>what they did</hi> but what <hi>it became the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> to haue done, by which reaſon, the honour of <hi>bonae memoriae</hi> belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth to <hi>Ieroboam</hi> amongſt the <hi>Kings, Balaam</hi> amongſt the <hi>Prophets, Iudas</hi> amongſt the <hi>Apostles.</hi> He muſt <hi>know</hi> all <hi>things, erre</hi> in <hi>nothing, direct, informe, animate, expound</hi> ſcriptures, <hi>canonize</hi> ſaints, <hi>forgiue ſins,</hi> create new <hi>Articles of faith,</hi> and in all theſe be as <hi>abſolute</hi> as his <hi>maker. He</hi> muſt encroach vpon the <hi>offices of Christ.</hi> His <hi>Kingdome, Prieſthood, Prophecie.</hi> O <hi>yee heavens</hi> bee aſtoniſhed at this, and let all <hi>Chriſtian hearts</hi> tremble to heare ſuch <hi>blaſphemies.</hi> Looke vpon all the <hi>ſucceſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from Pope Boniface</hi> 3 downeward,<note place="margin">D. Downam de Antich.</note> and you wil con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe it is <hi>Antichriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſay nothing of the now <hi>Pope Paule 5,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aunſwer to a nameles Cathol</note> 
               <hi>Burgheſius,</hi> but what the <hi>Seminarie Prieſts</hi> ſometimes ſpake of him: He is a <hi>raſh ſpeaker,</hi> a <hi>headie vndertaker,</hi> of a <hi>vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent ſpirit, impatient</hi> of <hi>contradiction.</hi> Hee challengeth the ſucceſſion of <hi>Peter,</hi> and name of <hi>Paul,</hi> but follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth neither. I ſearch not over farre, their orders of <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedict,</hi> which hath beene ſo fruitfull, that they ſay all the <hi>new orders</hi> which in latter times haue broken out are but little <hi>ſprings</hi>
               <note place="margin">Volladerius de Canoniza Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis Ro. in epiſt.</note> and <hi>drops,</hi> &amp; this the <hi>Ocean</hi> which hath ſent out 52 <hi>Popes,</hi> 200 <hi>Cardinals;</hi> 1600 <hi>Archbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops,</hi> 4000 <hi>Biſhops,</hi> &amp; 50000 <hi>Saints</hi> approued by the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:15637:17"/>Church. Looke on their <hi>pardons. Leo 10,</hi> for onely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſing the <hi>Lords Prayer,</hi> and thriſe repeating the name of <hi>Ieſus,</hi> gieuing 3000 yeares indulgence. <hi>Boni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face</hi> acknowledging ſo many <hi>Indulgences</hi> to be in that one Church of <hi>Lateran,</hi> that none but God can num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Indulgences</hi> are giuen not onely to the <hi>Franciſcans</hi> themſelues, but to their <hi>Parents,</hi> to any which die in their <hi>habits,</hi> to any which deſire they may doe ſoe, to thoſe who are wrapped in it after death, though they did not deſire it, and fiue yeares indulgence to thoſe who doe but kiſſe it.<note place="margin">Rodol Cupers de Eccl. vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varſ. fol <hi>4.</hi> Scappus de Iure non Scrip. l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>25.</hi>
               </note> Their <hi>Cardinals</hi> are ſo bound to the <hi>Pope,</hi> that it is not lawfull for them without li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe, firſt obtained from him to bee let <hi>bloud in a fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver,</hi> yet he calleth them his <hi>brothers, Princes</hi> of the world and <hi>Co-iudges</hi> of the whole earth.</p>
            <p>I leaue their <hi>Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Ieſuits,</hi> ſpirits of the Divell in many places of this land, breathing out infections, But <hi>bleſſed</hi> be the name of the Lord, who hath ſent vs a <hi>North wind,</hi> as is prophecied c. <hi>16.13.</hi> to driue away theſe <hi>Popiſh frogges</hi> to the place whence they came where they are dealt with as the old <hi>Romans</hi> did with their dogs in the <hi>capitol;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cic. proſex Roſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cio.</note> vnleſſe they did barke, their legges were broken, ſo theſe vnleſſe they libell againſt he worthieſt of our Saints, or often contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict things againſt <hi>conſcience,</hi> they haue neither <hi>coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance</hi> nor <hi>maintenance.</hi> I enter not into their <hi>Mona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries</hi> 225044, as <hi>Durus de Paſchalo</hi> reckons the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ep. Hulderic. Ep. Auguſt An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no <hi>866.</hi>
               </note> were the cauſe that there were 6000 Infants heades found in a fiſh-pond: neither lead you into their <hi>blou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:15637:18"/>inquiſitions,</hi> or <hi>horrid dungeons,</hi> but ende this circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance with that adviſe of S. <hi>Steven,</hi> O ſaue your ſelus from this wicked <hi>Antichriſtian</hi> generation; and ſo I haſten to my laſt part. The puniſhment of <hi>Babylon: plagues.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The plagues of <hi>Babylon</hi> for her perſecuting the Church are many, <hi>Mortalitie, Beaſts, Famine,</hi> c. 6.8. <hi>ſores, bloud ſhed</hi> by <hi>ſea and land,</hi> c. 9.10.11. <hi>wounding</hi> with the ſword, c. 13.14. <hi>vnſeaſonable &amp; diſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pred aires</hi> darkning her kingdom,<note place="margin">Doct.</note> c. 16. &amp; here <hi>plagues, Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce this doctrine</hi> appeareth. <hi>God in iuſtice will be revenged vpon the enimies of his Church.</hi> The proofs of this are many. What <hi>Tyra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t</hi> hath eſcaped without ſome iudgment?<note place="margin">Sueton.</note> 
               <hi>Domitian</hi> is ſlain with the daggers of his own ſerva<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, his <hi>wife</hi> conſenting. <hi>Adrian,</hi> after he had crucified at once ten thouſand Chriſtians, hath an iſſue of bloud, ſpitteth out his lungs,<note place="margin">Spartian. l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>12.</hi>
               </note> and is ſo afflicted with a <hi>Drop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie,</hi> that he would haue laid violent hands vpon him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe.<note place="margin">Euſ. hiſt. l. <hi>7.</hi> c. <hi>30.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Valerian</hi> by the meanes of the <hi>K of Perſia</hi> is flaied aliue, powdred with ſalt. <hi>Diocleſia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> thruſting the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians out of their offices, <hi>and burning their Bibles,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ruff.</note> had his houſe fired with lightning, &amp; himſelfe ſo ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified with thunder,<note place="margin">Niceph. chriſ.</note> that in a madneſſe he killed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. <hi>Maximinus,</hi> rotteth with wormes; and the <hi>apple of his eye</hi> falleth out. <hi>Aurelian</hi> hath his throat cut. <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rindus</hi> is devoured of a <hi>monſter</hi> that came out of the Iriſh ſeas. <hi>Cerinthus</hi> hath a hot houſe to fall vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him. <hi>Arrius</hi> voided his guts.<note place="margin">Nappier in A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poc. <hi>14.</hi> p. <hi>183.</hi>
               </note> So <hi>Rome</hi> muſt fall, but when, whether in the yeare of our <hi>Lord</hi> 1639, as ſome deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine it, I dare not conclude, or whether by the tenne
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:15637:18"/>hornes, c. 17.16. that is,<note place="margin">M. Dent.</note> as ſome inſinuate by the ten <hi>Kingdomes</hi> of <hi>Europe, England, Scotland, Germany, France, Spaine, Denmarke, Sueueland, Poland, Ruſsia,</hi> &amp; <hi>Hungary</hi> I will not ſearch. Wee knowe that of theſe, the <hi>beaſt</hi> hath loſt the <hi>moſt,</hi> the others in <hi>France, Spain</hi> and <hi>Venice,</hi> doe groane vnder the heauie yoke of the Pope, and muſt ſhake him of, ſo that the prophecies muſt be fulfilled, <hi>It is fallen, It is fallen,</hi> c. 14.8. A <hi>noy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome</hi> and grievous ſore ſhall fall vpon it. c. 16.2. Her plagues ſhall come in one day, <hi>death</hi> and <hi>mourning,</hi> &amp; <hi>famine,</hi> and ſhe ſhall be vtterly burnt with fire, c. 18.8. <hi>It ſhall be caſt downe like a great milstone into the bottom of the ſea.</hi> c. 18.21. <hi>The voice of Harpers and Muſitians,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 18.22,</note> 
               <hi>and Pipers, and Trumpetters, ſhall be heard no more in it. No crafts-man ſhall be found in it, nor the ſound of a mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone heard in it. The light of a candle ſhall ſhine no more in it. The voice of the bridegroome and the bride ſhall bee heard no more in it. The Lord doth the greateſt exploits either by himſelfe without</hi> meanes as he overthrew the <hi>Moabits</hi> and others. As he deſtroyed <hi>Pharaoh,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Chr. 20,</note> as he o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verthrew <hi>Iericho,</hi> &amp; the <hi>Aſsyrians.</hi> Or by weak meanes as the innumerable army of the <hi>Madianits</hi> by <hi>Gedeons</hi> 300. as the <hi>Philiſtins</hi> by <hi>Ionathan</hi> and his armour bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer. As the Kings of <hi>Sodome</hi> by <hi>Abraham,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iu 7.</note> and his fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>Goliah</hi> by <hi>David, Siſera</hi> by <hi>Iael.</hi> It is in vaine then to aske how <hi>Rome</hi> ſhall fall. God can doe it. Two <hi>founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> cannot ſtand at once. The Lord ſhall conſume that wicked man, with the breath of his mouth, and aboliſh him with the brightneſſe of his comming. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven ſo come <hi>Lord Ieſus,</hi> come quickly. So hee will,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:15637:19"/>though <hi>iniquitie</hi> for a while get the vpper hand, by corrupt <hi>ſubtiltie,</hi> by the proud and falſe vaunts of <hi>an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquitie, vniverſalitie,</hi> and <hi>ſucceſsion,</hi> By the glorious ſhewes of their <hi>proceſſions,</hi> the gaudy ornaments of their <hi>altars,</hi> the pomp of their <hi>ſervices,</hi> the triumphs of their <hi>feſtivals.</hi> By their taking the beſt <hi>opportunitie,</hi> to worke vpon thoſe which are either moſt vnable to reſiſt, or moſt like to <hi>beſtead them.</hi> By their rewards of the <hi>Calender</hi> or <hi>red-hat.</hi>
               <note place="margin">D. Hal in Ep.</note> By the conioynd <hi>labours</hi> of whole <hi>ſocieties,</hi> directed to one end, and ſhrouded vnder the title of one <hi>Author.</hi> By large <hi>maintenances</hi> rayſed from the <hi>death-beds of ſome giltie benefactors.</hi> By their pretended <hi>myracles,</hi> wilfull <hi>vntruths,</hi> bloudy <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſitions,</hi> depravation of ancient <hi>witneſſes,</hi> expurga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their own, condemnation of our <hi>writers,</hi> glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious titles, craftie <hi>changes</hi> of <hi>names, ſhapes, habits, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions,</hi> and <hi>multitudes of Actors.</hi> But we haue not ſo learned Chriſt, Wee haue receaued the plaine <hi>truth,</hi> Let vs ſtand faſt to it only. O let it never bee ſaid that our <hi>careleſneſſe,</hi> indifferencie, and idleneſſe ſhall ayde them, and wrong our ſelues. Wee haue a good <hi>King (and long may we haue him)</hi> who in the liſts of <hi>contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie,</hi> may grapple with <hi>Antichriſt</hi> for his triple crown. We haue thoſe <hi>Biſhops,</hi> who may iuſtly chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge the whole <hi>Conſiſtory of Rome.</hi> We haue as many learned <hi>Doctors,</hi> and true hearted <hi>Divines,</hi> as no nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vnder heauen more. <hi>Christendome</hi> hath not the like two <hi>flouriſhing Vniverſities.</hi> We want nothing, &amp; ſhall we <hi>be wanting</hi> to our ſelues. The cauſe is <hi>Gods,</hi> &amp; in ſpight of the <hi>gates</hi> of hell, ſhall ſucced, though we
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:15637:19"/>were not, our neglect may <hi>ſlacken</hi> the pace of <hi>truth,</hi> It cannot ſtay the paſſage. Our <hi>Honourable mother,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Anno <hi>880.</hi> Capgravius in Catalog. Sanct. Angl. <hi>884.</hi> Philippus chron. l. <hi>4.960.</hi> Balaeus Cent. <hi>2.1330.</hi> Wolphius lect. Memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rab. tom. <hi>1.</hi> Herod.</note> hath had a religious founder King <hi>Alfred</hi> that ſtood for the vſe of the Scripture to the <hi>Laitie</hi> againſt the <hi>Pope.</hi> Ioh. <hi>Patritius</hi> his Reader, that ſpake againſt <hi>tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiation,</hi> Many honeſt <hi>ſimple</hi> people that defended <hi>Rome</hi> to be <hi>Babylon. Occam</hi> that wrote a book againſt <hi>Pope Clement</hi> calling him <hi>Antichriſt.</hi> Let not vs goe backward.</p>
            <p>It is recorded of <hi>Craeſus,</hi> that being in danger to be <hi>ſlaine</hi> in the warre, his ſonne who had till that time beene <hi>dumbe,</hi> ſeeing his father in that eſtate, <hi>cryed out O man kill not Craeſus.</hi> Religion in many Places <hi>weepeth</hi> and is ready to <hi>bleed,</hi> If ever any amongſt vs were he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto <hi>ſilent,</hi> let their zeale now reuiue it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pyrrhus</hi> ſaid he woone more cities by the <hi>induſtrie</hi> of his Oratour <hi>Cineas,</hi> then he took by force of <hi>arms;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Plut. in Pyrrh.</note> Let our faithfull <hi>preaching</hi> the word without <hi>minſing</hi> or <hi>ſingularitie,</hi> or <hi>Popiſh</hi> and falſe <hi>allegations</hi> againſt thoſe bleſſed men of <hi>God, Calvin, Beza,</hi> &amp; the reſt, win more <hi>ſoules,</hi> then the circumventing <hi>ſtratagems</hi> of the <hi>Ieſuits.</hi> Let me ſpeake to you <hi>Nobly</hi> and <hi>Honourably</hi> deſcended <hi>flowers</hi> of this garden of the <hi>muſes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">To the hopefull ſonnes of the Honorab. The L. Montegle, The L. Peter, The L. Spenſer. S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Robert Carey</note> the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe of God, ſonnes of ſo worthy Fathers. Seaſon your <hi>ſtudies</hi> with the reading of the <hi>word,</hi> Let not the booke of the Law depart out of your hands, medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate in it day and night. Let the Poet encourage you.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Prima tuo gerito pro Iove bello puer.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mart.</note>
            </p>
            <p>To you, Reverend and learned <hi>worthies</hi> of our <hi>Iſrael,</hi> Let your reſolution be that of <hi>Luther, Non poteſt is
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:15637:20"/>ſalutem conſequi qui non ex toto corde Antichriſtum &amp; Papatum oderit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let your farewell to your friends, bee as was that of the late <hi>memorable</hi> &amp; learned <hi>D. Holland, Commendo vos dilectioni Dei &amp; odio Papatus,</hi> Exhort them all to loue God, &amp; hate Popery. To all let my adviſe be, that of Ier, 50, 14. <hi>Put your ſelues in aray againſt Babylo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> round about</hi> (againſt <hi>Rome</hi>) <hi>All yee that hend the bowe ſhoot at her,</hi> ſpare no arrowes, for ſhe hath ſinned <hi>againſt the Lord.</hi> Doe to <hi>her</hi> as ſhe hath done to <hi>others,</hi> ſo for our zeale, God ſhall bleſſe vs, and crowne vs in his glorious <hi>Kingdome,</hi> whether hee bring vs, who died for vs, even Chriſt <hi>Ieſus,</hi> to whom with the <hi>Father,</hi> and the <hi>Spirit,</hi> be aſcribed all <hi>glory,</hi> and honour this day, and forever. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:15637:20"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
